These are several tech tips I accumulated.

Tip: Releasing / Uncapturing the keyboard input focus when using a KVM / virt-manager VM

In order to release the keyboard input focus when using KVM (Kernel-based Virtual Machine) and virt-manager one can press "left control" and "left alt" together (not "left shift"). This was described in this post from StackExchange, where it shows how to set it to a different key combination.

This was another post emulating Lisha Sterling's old "know where the ledge is" blog (which seems to have disappeared).

Tip: Vim: Setting a different X.org/X11 Connection

If you are using Vim or neovim and wish to set a different X.org connection (e.g: for copy+paste), you can use :let $DISPLAY = 'myremotehost.tld:0.0'. Other environment variables can be changed or set in a similar way using the dollar-sign notation.

Tip: GFile type in python3 / gi / Gio / Gtk+

The GFile type in python can be retrieved using the following idiom:

import gi
from gi.repository import Gio

FILE_TYPE = Gio.File.__gtype__

# Use FILE_TYPE

Tip: Search for file paths by pattern using DNF (on Fedora / CentOS / etc)

Using DNF one can search for file paths which are contained in uninstalled packages (similar to apt-file on Debian / Ubuntu / etc. or urpmf on Mageia) using dnf whatprovides '/usr/bin/start*'.

Licence

Copyright by Shlomi Fish, 2020.

You can reuse this entry under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported licence, or at your option any later version of it. See the instructions on how to comply with it.

Whatever code given here is provided under the MIT / Expat licence.

Report on the Alphageeks meeting

I went to a meeting of an Israeli computers group called "Alphageeks" today and would like to write a report about it when my memory is still fresh.

I was a little tardy this time, because I got prepared late and left home even later, but the first presentation still did not start when I got there a few minutes after the schedule. It took me a lot of time to find the building, because I did not print a good map in advance and instead relied on my memory of the general location of the place and people's directions.

One thing I noticed was that the location left a lot to be desired. The building is old, the stairs suffered from a lot of decay, and the elevator did not seem to work, nor could really be trusted (as someone I left with said later on). I ended up at a studio apartment on the third floor without too many chairs, with a fridge and a counter with a lot of food and drink (including many beer bottles - I don't drink but it seemed like a nice bonus), and with many people there. Since I didn't have a chair, I opted to stand during the two talks that I stayed to watch.

The first thing we did was a round of introductions

In any case, I placed the bottle of juice that I had bought on the way on the counter, took a cup from a different bottle of juice (Lemonade - yum.) and went to stand and watch the talk about HTML 5. While it was as a general rule, not a very technical talk, it was pretty cool, explaining the history of HTML 5, some of the new features that we can expect from it, and a lot of promise. We discussed the fact that Internet Explorer is still lagging behind other browsers in its support for even older standards, and I was disappointed to find out that MSIE 9 still does not support .xhtml or the application/xml content-type. We also discussed CSS 3, and the presenter said that CSS 2.1 was already good enough, and that we could live without gradients or rounded corners.

He mentioned that his web-design process works by getting a page style as an image from his graphics' designer, sending it somewhere ("to India, etc.") and getting a 100% squeaky clean and semantic XHTML design, and then using jQuery to communicate with the JSON API, and stuff like that.

Then there was a break, where I ended up discussing my grand unified vision for a typesetting system I'm writing as an alternative to TeX and LaTeX, and also asked a little about XSL-FO and Apache FOP, and we concluded that good internationalisation may be a problem with some of the XSL-FO implementations. The Apache FOP people told me they would rather not implement Bi-directionality (e.g: mixed Arabic/Hebrew/etc. and Latin) until version 1.0 and the last release was 0.95 since 13 months ago.

Cython: Report and Tips

Cython allows one to compile code written using a superset of the Python programming language into C code for improved performance. I recently tried it in an attempt to speed up my solution to a Project Euler problem, which was ran slowly, even by pypy. After some amount of work, the cython-based solution outperformed the pure-Python code, without me having to reimplement it all in C or C++ or similar. So you too should consider using it, if you need the extra performance.

The rest of this post contains some Cython tips for using it well that I discovered in my (so far relatively limited) experimentation with it.

I noticed that cdef int i; for in xrange(0, mymax) does not get optimised while cdef int i; for i in range(mymax); does.

cdef int arr[100][100] declares a local array of 100*100 elements , and keeps copying it, which is likely not what you want. On the other hand, cdef int [100] * ptr generates a pointer.

“cdef” cannot be used inside loops.

It is a good idea to declare the C types as late as possible - only right before the time-critical code when you absolutely need to use them. One can initialize them from dynamically-typed python data structures.

One can copy+paste the compiler's invocation command on the command line and edit it to apply better optimisation flags. There may be a way to customise the compilation command by editing the “setup.py” file, but I didn't bother to figure it out yet.

One can and should inspect the generated .c file to see the resultant C code to see if anything is done sub-optimally.

Licence

Copyright by Shlomi Fish, 2017.

You can reuse this entry under the Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported licence, or at your option any later version of it. See the instructions on how to comply with it.

The Lost Souls of Freenode

I originally wanted to write a more prose-like blog post about the topic of “The Lost Souls of Freenode”, echoing some of my frustrations from trying to help people on Freenode channels, especially #perl and ##programming and I started from keeping a list of bullets and sub-bullets and decided to keep it this way out of being lazy. Maybe it can also be considered the blog equivalent of some wikiHow pages.

After I gave a link to the bullets to someone I met on Freenode, he told me he hasn't found any of what he read here surprising from his experience on IRC and as a tutor and T.A. (= Teacher Assistant) in an American college.

“Many Lost Souls” on Freenode's #perl - IM conversation.

Quote the conversation about “First rule of #perl channels” (meaning that Freenode’s #perl is our first line of defence).

People having problems getting indentation right.

People who /msg me after asking.

Either they think that's the way to answer.

Or they think that I cannot help them because there's another conversation.

They're usually not willing or cannot afford to pay.

Someone who thought that paying me 50 USD / hour for private help was too high.

People who want us to write their code for them.

“Help me with a script I found.”

Often badly written.

“Help me with using a program / my operating system / etc.”

Not even related to coding.

“Are you using version control?” “No, what's that?”

Automated tests?

A debugger?

Old versions of perls.

Homework/scholastic constraints.

“We didn't study it yet”

“No external modules / CPAN”

“Not allowed to use any built-in language data structures, including not arrays.”

Mandatory course.

Graded 0 once because was programmed on Python-2.7.x and tested on Python-3.3.x (on Windows).

One who didn't know what files are nor did file I/O.

He only used the Ruby REPL directly (for short and ephemeral programs).

private conversation with someone else who didn't know what files are.

Web Development Has Become Too Hard

Web development has become too hard. It's not nostalgia - it's been a while since it has been easy, and I'm not sure it ever was. But in any case, the past does not matter - it is very very hard.

Linus Torvalds commented that: User space developers are weenies. One of the most fun parts of git development for me has been how easy everything is.. Well, git confuses me and many other people who starts with it; often emits obscure error messages and refuses to do many operations that require me to consult other people on how to proceed; it tends to emit over-verbose error messages; it lacks a good external or internal API ; and it has been the topic of an excessive amount of blog posts explaining obscure ways to do various processes in the "Grand Unified Theory of Version Control Using Git", a potential thesis subject of some Ph.D. diplomas. (that was sarcasm.). So I'm not sure Torvalds did a very good job.

However, designing command line applications is easy, as I can testify (though some people fail to do it too), and designing APIs is not much harder. But what about web development? I once attended a supper after a Linux-Herzeliya meeting where an open source contractor said something along these lines: "Some people think that web-development is easier than kernel development, but it's really not true. It's actually harder. Just getting everything to work with Internet Explorer 6 is excruciatingly difficult.". Of course, the more I thought about it recently, the more I concluded that supporting Internet Explorer 6 (which some web-sites including my own have decided to avoid recently) is just the tip of the iceberg of how hard contemporary web-development is.

The Past

The Internet.

"The Net is the Computer"

HTTP and HTML - Hypertext Transfer Protocol and Markup Language.

The Web Becomes a "General" Application Platform

New daily buzzwords

Case study: www.shlomifish.org

I maintain a personal web-site on www.shlomifish.org. It is large and contains essays, articles, stories, aphorisms and quotes, presentation materials, information about myself, links to open-source software I've worked on and many other resources. I enjoy working on it, and many people who stumbled upon it or I referred them to it have complimented me on it and said that they enjoyed some of it.

Here are some factors that facilitate my work on the site:

The site is almost completely static data and the server just serves the files as is. In order to have a common look and feel, I generate the pages from templates, text and other data using my own off-line CMS, which I invoke from the command line on my local computer, it generates the final site and I then update it on the server. The off-line CMS is open-source, but it's besides the point.

I recently dropped support for MSIE 6 and may not support MSIE 7 either. My pages broke with IE 6 and I could not bother to hack around it and I have an anti-IE page.

Despite all that, the site has the following problems:

It fails to render properly when the font sizes are increased too much (somewhere past 20pt IIRC). While this is quite unusual, some people - especially those who have a poor eyesight may opt to use it and thus the site is less usable for them. Someone on webdesign-L who pointed me to it, has given me some fixed CSS but he didn't test it and I didn't know where to put it and whether it will work at all, so I didn't pursue this direction.

Some people have complained about the site's width being either too narrow or too wide. The site uses a fixed-width layout (because that is what the original WordPress design that I based my efforts on used), and so there's no one-size-fits-all.

The separators between the links in the bottom are not properly middle aligned and I don't know how to fix it. (Very minor problem but it is still annoying.)

Like I said, the site does not work properly in MSIE 6, which in a perfect world would be easy to do.

One cannot comment on the pages. I added Disqus JavaScript-based comments once, but I believed they made the site much slower, and the fact that they started loading Google Analytics, which I want to avoid was the last straw and I removed them. Now if I wanted to add comments, I'll need to either find a different JavaScript-comments provider, or alternatively implement comments myself using a server-side scripting solution.

Despite that, my site still requires Google Analytics due to the ShareThis button I placed there. While I like the functionality that ShareThis provides to people who visit my site, I'm unhappy with its Analytics requirement. When I contacted ShareThis about this they told me "At this time, there is no way to disable our widget from accessing Google Analytics.", so I need to hack something in Perl or whatever to render the link sharing buttons in order to avoid ShareThis and subsequently Google Analytics. I haven't done it yet.

The colours of the background layout images are a little off on my stationary computer's LCD screen and completely off on my laptop's screen. I intend to fix it, but didn't yet get to it.

Benjamin Frankling is misquoted as saying that "To find out a girl's faults, praise her to her girl friends." (he did say something similar more verbosely). Similarly, at the two times I have published revisions of my essay "Create a Great Personal Homesite", people took the opportunity to criticise my home site, in order to demonstrate how smart they were in demonstrating how much I didn't practise what I preached, instead of what I said in the essay itself. So if you want to discover problems with your site, then publishing such an essay would be a sure-fire way to see what people think of it, despite the fact that their own sites may have a fraction of the useful content of your site (or mine for that matter).

Naturally, all the problems I mention here are just the current state of the site. Many more were solved along the way, and the time I invest in solving such problems, could be invested in adding more content to the site, which is what actually attracts people to it. I am a mostly one-man team in maintaining www.shlomifish.org and do not have a lot of monetary resources at my disposal to invest in it (so I cannot afford to hire a good CSS designer, for example).

Don't get me wrong: many people have complimented me or thanked me for the many resources they found on the site and I'm happy to hear from them. But I always have the nagging feeling that not everyone are happy, or that I can never please everyone, or that people like complaining for the sake of complaining to show how smart they are and are never happy. Luckily, I'm not a perfectionist, but still the point is that it would take too much effort to create a site that functions perfectly.

The Problem with The Web Today

In order to do good web design today, you need to first learn HTML/XHTML, CSS and most probably JavaScript as well. While the situation is much better than a few years ago, different browsers still have different quirks and different problems with implementing the standards for them (especially Internet Explorer 6, which many sites still need to support). Then you'll need to design an attractive site that will be look adequately everywhere. Some designers only give you a big image (PSD, etc.) of the web-site's layout that they expect you to slice and dice and convert to XHTML+CSS yourself, and there are services (such as PSD2HTML) that will do it for you ("Starting at $159."), or you can do it yourself. If you're a good designer, you might be able to do the CSS and images work yourself.

A few problems along the way are: 1. CSS positioning being the hard, quirky and counter-intuitive monster that it is. 2. Browser incompatibilities. 3. Having to learn a good JavaScript abstraction library, such as jQuery, and hope that you won't have to learn another one when working on a different project.

Now once we are done with the client-side code (which is much easier on paper), we are going to the server-side. Here you have to deal with the HTTP protocol, with various potential holes such as SQL injection, Cross-site scripting (a.k.a "HTML injection" or XSS), Cross-site request forgery (CSRF), and simple design bugs that may escalate into security problems. Even if your web application is perfectly secure, it still does not mean that it doesn't have usability bugs or general usability issues.

And then naturally, there's the choice of server-side technology: Perl, Python, PHP, Ruby, ASP, ASP.NET, Java/JSP, ColdFusion, Erlang, Haskell, C++, server-side JavaScript, Squeak Smalltalk and many more obscure technologies. And after you've done choosing a technology, you still need to choose the web-development framework or content-management system. In Perl alone the choice of web-development frameworks includes CGI-Application (and Titanium), CGI-Application-Plus, CGI-Builder, CGI-Prototype, Jifty, Catalyst (and Reaction), Mojo, SweetPea, Dancer, Gantry, AxKit, WebGUI and I've heard of some new ones under development. Each such framework comes with its own APIs to learn, bugs and mis-features to be aware of, new surprises and a whole lot of stuff to learn as you go.

When I worked on a web-based mailing list software for an Israeli company, it was decided to convert the existing PHP codebase to the Symfony web framework. It took me a while to get the demo application to work, and afterwards I had problems with the database abstraction layer there leaking memory (which made me have to resort to using the old mysql interface). Moreover, the recent versions of PHP (in a minor third digit release) broke compatibility with the testing framework that Symfony standardised on, which made it harder for us to write tests, unless we would have upgraded the test framework to its non-officially-released beta.

The motivation for converting the code to Symfony was to improve its quality, but one day I glimpsed at some code that my co-workers were working on, and while it has been using the framework conventions, was still clearly horrible code. So using a web-development framework was not sufficient for having elegant code.

Why E-mail is not only a Todo list

This is a essay that aims to be a correction to what Paul Graham wrote:

Email was not designed to be used the way we use it now. Email is not a messaging protocol. It's a todo list. Or rather, my inbox is a todo list, and email is the way things get onto it. But it is a disastrously bad todo list.

I'm open to different types of solutions to this problem, but I suspect that tweaking the inbox is not enough, and that email has to be replaced with a new protocol. This new protocol should be a todo list protocol, not a messaging protocol, although there is a degenerate case where what someone wants you to do is: read the following text.

While it seemed to have made a little sense at first, I eventually realised that there are other resources whose functionality I use as a to-do list aside from email. For example:

My browser's bookmarks’ menu where I bookmark links to deal with.

My home directory and other directories on my file system where I put non-permanent files.

Non-committed files in version control repositories.

Bug trackers / issue trackers.

Actual to-do lists I keep and manage.

However, there are other aspects for their use aside from serving as a to-do list, and they are all different from one another.

As a result, while trying to create an alternative to E-mail is commendable, I suspect that trying to replace E-mail with a to-do-list-like protocol will not prove to be popular, because like those - E-mail is not exclusively a to-do list.